.
So we are talking about value functions okay
people remember value functions is we define
value functions we said
V? (S)= to expected value under ? of right.
And then we defined Q? .Right good, so now
we are going to start unrolling their expectation
and so people remember this expression right
so all of your player but I don't have to
explain what is happening there again right
so V? (s) is means starting in status following
policy ? . Thereafter and taking the expectations
of the, the returns that I am getting I am
going to start unrolling this right so what
does it what does it look like so
i am going to say V? (s) equal to, yes
What can right here, I GT+1 right but what
is what would be the value of GT+ for the
expected value of GT+1.V? off whatever state
you land up in right so let us go I am going
to say that this is equal to
V? (s) prime were s prime is the state I am
going to add up and we will quantify as Prime
in a minute right so, so people agree with
me on this right is s prime is the state I
go to from s right so I can take this summation
and write it like this. Everybody on board
okay great so now I need a slight slight of
hand here right so I took GT and then I wrote
it as one term plus the expected value of
GT but that is fine because I am anyway going
to take a expectation eventually right so
this is slight reordering of expectations
right instead of taking an expectation of
the full expression.
I took the expectation of the inner one alone
but one thing you have to remember is it is
only a partial expectation because s prime
can change right so for me to get the full
expectation i need to condition on s prime
also
That is why this expression is still inside
the expectation so if this has been the full
expectation we are taking it out, out of the
expectation since it is still only partially
conditioned so I need to conditioned on the
full thing okay so now I have to write it
out so that will get rid of the expectations
okay so one way of writing out this expectation
is to think of it like a generative process
okay.
So remember what did I say we are going to
do we'll start in state s right then select
actions according to policy ? right and measure
the, expected return right so the starting
in state is and the selecting actions according
to policy ?.
So what does that mean
using ? right and I am selecting actions according
to policy ? so let us say I pick some action
a right so now what I am going to do I am
going to get some reward corresponding to
that RT+ yeah the RT+1 will be something that
corresponds to that reward so but then.Before
I can find out what RT +1 this I need to specify
what the next state is going to be so I need
this.
So taken action a then I determine what s
prime is and then I determine
What
but I already determined what s prime is it
so
I can do this
right so this is one step I am taking a pick
an action a according to ? right now that
is going to cause a transition to some s Prime
according to this P that we have that right
and once I know what the S prime is I can
figure out what the expected reward will be
as well as V? (s) prime because I know what
is frame is so what is the probability that
this will be my return is this times the probability
i will pick action so this whole thing gives
me the probability that this will be my expected
return okay so now i have to do this overall
all possible outcomes.
So basically a sum over spray okay is it clear
how we got this right this one right so i
have a s a right that i picked a a first then
I pick an s Prime according to p now I have
a SA S prime so what I need to do is figure
out what this our expectation of RT+1 would
be right so that is given in my MDP right
the expectation of RT+1 would be given SA
S prime.
What is the reward so that is this expectation
I've written it here expectation of are given
SAS prime right and then the future is ? V?(s)
prime so that S Prime has already been fixed
so I can just add the ? beep is prime here.
So the probability that this will be the outcome
right is the probability of s prime given
S and A time's the probability of picking
A given is S .
So all these things put together gives me
the probability that this will be the outcome
right so that is the expected outcome for
one choice of A and one choice of S prime
so I'll have to sum this overall choices of
S prime and all choices of A for me to get
the overall expectation so that is essentially
what I've done here ?xI ?a .
This is nice right so we written V? in terms
of V?. So this, this system of it is a system
of equations right you can see there is a
system of equations that you have one equation
for every, every state how many variables
are there number of as many variables as there
are number of states the number of states
is not the variable that is also fixed as
many variables as number of states and what
is a very we here V?(s) is the variable.
So essentially so in some thinking of it as
a function now I can think of it as a collection
of variables right one for each state right
and I have N such equations and N such variables
and can I solve it. Depends on what, its linear
N variables in equations so when can you not
solve it yeah then ,then then yeah certainly
get dependent columns and so it becomes redundant
so you have multiple solutions and sorts of
three so it turns out as I'll show you in
the next class right the system of equations
have a unique solution.
Always right by virtue of the fact that the
P that you are using is stochastic so the
rows of that P matrix will come to one right
so by virtue of that fact we can actually
go back and show that there will be a unique
solution for this need to write, write is
slightly different in a different notation
for us to see that so I will do that in the
next class right so this is free which has
a unique solution and this is sometimes known
as
The Bellman Equation for V? after the Richard
Bellman who's one of the pioneers in the field
of stochastic dynamic programming okay. Like
ways you can write a bellman equation for
Q? okay. Satan wants to tell me about the
bellman equation for Q? would be
So think of it in the generative process right
so what is the first thing you do when you're
thinking about Q?SA .They start with yes I
pick a right I mean it is fixed so there is
no summing over there right it's S and A is
picked right so what do I have to sum over
next only the Express because this ?(a/s)
is out of the picture here right because I
have already picked A . So I do not need to
I do not need to sample from ? they already
pick case so I just start my summing over
s prime.
But now, now SA is prime are all fixed right
so I can write expected value of R given SA
s prime plus ? times.
Now the interesting question is what goes
there I could write V? and it will be perfectly
correct but I will not be writing Q? in terms
of Q?.
Sum over all actions
Use a Bellman Equation for Q? okay.
So this should also give you one, one more
ancillary equation there which is.
And that is
a way Q and V are related and what about Q?
can you write Q? in terms of V? .But exactly
what the earlier equation was the Bellman
Equation substitute the last summation with
V? and that is essentially Q? in terms of
V?. Right so I cannot write Q? SE in terms
of V?s it has to be in terms of V? of the
subsequent state right but V? is I can write
in terms of Q? oops sorry.